Finding Aid for Dudley Maynard Phelps paper, 1920-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dudley Maynard Phelps papers 1920-1990, 1939-1961
Phelps, Dudley Maynard.
3 linear feet
2013121 Aa 2
Dudley Maynard Phelps was a student in the University of Michigan School of Business Administration's first graduating class, a University of Michigan faculty member (1926-1966), and an American diplomat during, and immediately following, World War II. His papers consist of correspondence, memoranda, research notes, Department of State records, publications, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This record group (donor no. 10947 ) was received in June, 2013.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Dudley Maynard Phelps was Professor of Marketing at the University of Michigan School of Business Administration (1926-1966) and a United States diplomat during World War II and the post-war reparations process. He was born May 8, 1897, to Charles and Cora Phelps in Manton, Michigan. Phelps completed his entire higher-level education at the University of Michigan, graduating with the first undergraduate class of the School of Business Administration in 1925, earning his MBA in 1926, and PhD in 1931.
During his tenure at the University of Michigan Phelps served on several university committees and received the Distinguished Faculty Award. Beginning as an Instructor in the School of Business Administration in May 1926, he was eventually appointed as full Professor of Marketing in July 1941. He was a member of the American Marketing Association, acting as its Director in 1939 and its President from 1957 to 1958. The American Marketing Association awarded Phelps the Parlin Award and Hall of Fame in Distribution Award in 1964. Phelps conducted significant international research, including the study of the immigration of American industry into Latin America in Argentina, the development of rubber manufacturing in Brazil, and lecturing at Waseda University in Japan. He headed the official U.S. exchange delegation to study marketing and distribution practices in the Soviet Union. He developed the Netherlands' first business program in cooperation with the Netherlands School of Economics in Rotterdam.
Phelps briefly left the University of Michigan between 1942 and 1946 to work for the U.S. Department of State, holding positions in Venezuela, Washington D.C., and Western Europe. He served as the Associate Chief, Division of Financial and Monetary Affairs to the U.S. Embassy in Venezuela. In 1945 he became deeply involved in the reparations process following World War II, serving as a member of the Rosenman Mission to Western Europe, Deputy Delegate to the Paris Conference on Reparations, and U.S. Representative to the Inter-Allied Reparations Agency. Following this assignment, he returned to the University of Michigan in 1946, remaining at the university until his retirement in June 1966. He passed away on January 1, 1993. He had a wife, Mildred, and two children Marcia and Richard.
The Dudley M. Phelps papers contain substantial information related to reparations calculations after World War II and the study of marketing and distribution practices in the Soviet Union during the Cold War. Researchers will also be interested in information regarding the first graduating class of the University of Michigan School of Business Administration. The collection comprises of 2.6 linear feet composed mainly of correspondence, memoranda, research notes, reports, and photographs. The collection is arranged into four series: UM School of Business Administration, Department of State, Post-Retirement, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Business education--Study and teaching.; Marketing--Study and teaching.; Marketing research--United States.; Phelps, Dudley Maynard.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Business Administration.; World War, 1939-1945--Reparations.; Goodman, Marshall I.; Rosenman, Samuel I. (Samuel Irving), 1896-1973.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Phelps, Dudley Maynard.; Rubber industry--Brazil.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Business Administration.; War damage.; World War, 1939-1945--Destruction and pillage--Europe.; World War, 1939-1945--Reparations.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- University of Michigan School of Business Administration 1928-1969
  The series UM School of Business Administration, 1928-1969 (1.3 linear feet), is arranged alphabetically. The bulk of the collection is correspondence, but it also contains research notes, reports, annual teaching reports, memoranda, grant applications, speeches, itineraries, bibliographic materials, and a bibliography. This series contains materials related to his research trips in the Soviet Union, Argentina, Brazil, and the Netherlands and to his work for the American Marketing Association.
  - American Marketing Association Presidency 1957-1958 (Box 1)
  - American Marketing Association -- Waseda, Japan 1966 (Box 1)
  - Annual Teaching Documents and Faculty Record 1948-1967 (Box 1)
  - "Automotive Design and the Public Interest," 1967 (Box 1)
  - Awards and Retirement 1961-1969 (Box 1)
  - Brazil Rubber Study Correspondence 1951-1952 (Box 1)
  - Brazil Rubber Study Research Notes 1951-1953 (Box 1)
  - Business School and Biographical Materials 1928-1966 (Box 1)
  - "Economic Relations with Latin America," 1940 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Award, The 1961 (Box 1)
  - Family Correspondence, Argentina Research Trip 1932-1933 (Box 1)
  - Firestone's Proposal for a Rubber Plantation in Brazil 1953 (Box 1)
  - Ford Foundation Fellowship Account #32144 1959-1961 (Box 1)
  - Hall of Fame in Distribution Award 1961 (Box 1)
  - Japan, Waseda University, Postcards 1958 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Rotterdam, Netherlands 1967 (Box 1)
  - Logical Methods Research Notes undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1934-1959 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1961-1971 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1937-1972, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Draft Publications and Research Notes undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Family Correspondence, Brazil Research Trip 1954 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous First Business School Class Memorabilia undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Speeches and Addresses undated (Box 1)
  - Notes on Economic Theory and its Origins undated (Box 1)
  - Parlin Award Letters and Addresses 1964 (Box 1)
  - "Report on the Present System of Rubber Production in Brazil and a Proposal for a Systematic Rubber Planting Program," 1952 (Box 1)
  - Rotterdam, Netherlands Business School Development, Miscellaneous Files 1965-1969, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Trip to the U.S.S.R., Miscellaneous Correspondence 1960-1961 (Box 2)
  - Trip to the U.S.S.R., Miscellaneous Notes and Publications 1960-1961 (Box 2)
  - U.S.S.R. Trip, Miscellaneous Reports and Publications 1960-1961 (Box 2)
  - U.S.S.R. Trip Research, Marshall Goldman, "Around the World in 95 Days" draft 1964 (Box 2)
- Department of State 1942-1946
  The series Department of State, 1942-1946 (0.8 linear feet), is arranged alphabetically. The series includes material from working in Washington D.C., Venezuela, and Western Europe following World War II. The bulk of the material focuses on his reparations work in Western Europe with the Rosenman Mission and Paris Conference on Reparations, and consists of mainly correspondence and memoranda. In addition, the materials related to post-World War II Western Europe contain research notes, reparations calculations, itineraries, press materials, Department of State bulletins, and drafts of reports and resolutions from the reparations process.
  - Caracas, Venezuela, Business Correspondence 1942-1943 (Box 2)
  - Foreign Investment Notes 1943-1945 (Box 2)
  - Inter-Allied Reparations Agency Press Materials
    - Inter-Allied Reparations Agency Press Materials, 1945 (Box 2)
    - Inter-Allied Reparations Agency Press Materials, 1948 (Box 2)
  - Inter-Allied Reparations Agency Miscellaneous Materials 1945-1946 (Box 2)
  - Letters from Paris 1945-1946 (Box 2)
  - Letters from Western Europe, Rosenman Mission or Reparations Delegation 1945-1946 (Box 2)
  - Letters to Mildred from Washington, D.C. (after Caracas) 1943 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1943-1945 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1945-1948 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Department of State Correspondence 1939-1946 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Family Correspondence, Caracas, Venezuela undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Reparations Materials 1945-1946 (Box 2)
  - Paris Conference on Reparations, Office 1945-1946 (Box 2)
  - Rosenman Mission Miscellaneous Materials 1945-1946 (Box 2)
  - Rosenman Mission and Reparations Delegation, Other Materials 1945-1946 (Box 2)
  - U.S. Reparations Delegation, Paris 1945-1982
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1945 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Reports & Memoranda 1945 (Box 2)
    - "The Distribution of Reparation from Germany," 1946 (Box 2)
    - "German Reparation and Restitution after World War II," 1982 (Box 2)
  - Venezuela, Miscellaneous Materials 1942-1943 (Box 2)
- Post-Retirement 1972-1990
  - Alice Culver/Dudley M. Phelps Correspondence 1975-1984 (Box 3)
  - International Marketing Federation 1972-1973, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Interview Transcripts with Dudley M. Phelps 1990 (Box 3)
    (for tapes, see Related Materials note)
- Visual Materials 1920-1926, 1954-1976
  - UM School of Business Administration
    - American Marketing Association, Charter Presentation Dinner 1958 (Box 3)
    - American Marketing Association Presidency Photographs 1957-1958 (Box 3)
    - Brazil Rubber Study Photographs 1954 (Box 3)
    - Brazil Trip Photograph from Correspondence 1954 (Box 3)
    - Business School Class Photographs 1971-1976, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Business School Class Photographs undated, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Executive Development Program 1955 (Box 3)
    - Executive Development Program 1961 (Box 3)
    - Executive Development Program 1964 (Box 3)
    - Japan, Waseda University, Scrapbooks 1958, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Business School Photographs undated, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Family Photographs undated (Box 3)
    - Pi Kappa Alpha 1920-1924 (Box 3)
    - School of Business Administration 1926 (Box 3)
    - U.S.S.R. Trip Photographs 1961 (Box 3)
  - Department of State
    - Family Photograph from Venezuela Correspondence undated (Box 3)
    - Rosenman Mission and Reparations Delegation photographs 1945-1946, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Rosenman Mission -- Unidentified Photographs undated (Box 3)